A while back, I had the pleasure of
interviewing Robin on her experience
using weighted vests. And in that
interview, I went over a lot of the
science behind these weighted vests. But
instead of regurgitating the same
information, like a cat vomiting a
furball, I'd like to introduce some new
information coming from a small study
that discovered two things that happen
when you wear a weighted vest. In said
study, the researchers wanted to find
out what happens when people use
weighted vests and the impact that has
on long-term weight loss as well as
people's metabolism. So, they recruited
18 people. This was a pilot study, so it
wasn't meant to be a huge study and
randomly assigned them to a calorie
deficit diet or a calorie deficit diet
including weighted vest use. These
people were overweight and surprisingly
they also reported having
osteoarthritis. I say that's surprising
because uh a weighted vest can really be
quite burdensome. Yet, these individuals
were able to use these vests regularly
for 6 months. What's cool about this
study is that uh while they were
actively trying to lose weight and body
fat for 6 months, the researchers wanted
to know what happens over the longer
term. So, over 2 years. In fact, the
vesties, as I shall call these people
using the weighted vests, only wore them
for 6 months, not the following year and
a half afterwards. The researchers point
that uh people struggle to maintain
weight loss over years and even if there
is initial success. They mention two
reasons for that. One is the hormonal
changes that we've uh been aware of for
some time. For example, if we lose body
fat, our fat cells called adiposytes
secrete less of a hormone called leptin.
This hormone when you're wellfed binds
to a region of your brain called the
hypothalamus. And the neurons there, the
brain cells, activate to reduce your
feelings of hunger. Since you're not
wellfed when you're losing body fat, at
least physiologically speaking, your
adiposytes reduce leptin release,
meaning less binds to the hypothalamus,
and the opposing neurons that stimulate
hunger become more active. That's
probably the most influential mechanism
that researchers discuss. But make no
mistake, there are other hormones like
ghrein will increase release from your
stomach or peptide y will reduce or be
less active after meal consumption.
There's plenty more. Still, the focus on
leptin is apt because the second reason
that the researchers focus on is what's
known as the gravitto hypothesis, which
has little to do with your stomach, but
has to do with your bones. That's right,
your bones. I cover this in much more
detail in my discussion with Robin, so
I'll link it below. But the idea is that
your bone cells also release hormones as
they sense the pressure applied to them.
Hopefully, you're seeing where the
weighted vests might come in here. When
you stand, the weight of your body
presses down on your bones in your legs.
Inside those bones are cells called
osteocytes. I'll show you a real picture
of what they look like. It's really
cool. And these cells encase themselves
surrounded by bone structure. Now, in
doing so, they extend projections out to
feel their surroundings. So think of you
like holding your hand up against the
wall and pushing against that wall. Now
if that wall flexes inward from the
pressure being applied from the outside,
you'll sense it in your hand like
osteoccytes do. Once sensed, the
osteoccytes release leptin independent
molecules that bind the same area of
your brain, the hypothalamus, and
influence your food consumption, but
also your metabolism, which we'll get
to. Anyway, if you suddenly load more
weight on you, your bones have to sense
that and release these molecules. But in
humans, do we see weighted vests having
any lasting impact? If we look at the
weight loss data, we can see the weight
change on the vertical axis and the
further it goes down, the better. The
black line is the calorierestricted diet
only and the dotted is the same but
including the weighted vest. So the
vestes
remember people were only monitored to
maintain their diet for 6 months and we
see equal weight loss. Nothing really
revolutionary there. However, look at
the 2-year time point there. The people
who didn't wear a weight vest regained
all the weight. Fascinatingly, those
that wore the vest, while they did seem
to regain some weight, they were able to
maintain some of the lost weight. The
really incredible thing here is that
these people aren't wearing the vest
anymore. So, the vest clearly did
something to their physiology or
something else positive happened that
led to them being able to get better
long-term results. But possibly more
impressive is what happens to their
metabolism. By the way, I've covered
several studies on weighted vests. And
across multiple studies, I've designed a
protocol for how to use weighted vests
to achieve the best results, like what
weight to use, how often, and more. All
of that with the lowest risk and the
least effort. I offered for the
Physionic Insiders if you're interested
in trying it out. You also get access to
a ton of other perks, too. Live sessions
with me to ask questions. We could
discuss your journey using a weighted
vest if you want along with written
research reviews, a library of other
protocols and guides, exclusive videos,
and a private podcast that you can
listen to while you wear your weighted
vest. Again, all Physionic Insider
included. The link is in the
description. Check it out. If uh we look
at the metabolism data, we can see the
change in resting metabolic rate on the
vertical axis. This time, if it goes
down, it's worse. Here's the surprising
part across multiple fronts. One, the
weighted vest retains metabolism while
caloric deficit reduces it. That alone
is a fascinating finding. The next thing
is that metabolism is maintained
presumably over the 2 years. So even
after weight loss and after ceasing
weighted vest use, there's still a
maintenance of metabolism. Now there's a
bit of assumption here. I should mention
because we're only looking at three time
points with an 18month gap between six
and 24 months. But more remarkable to
me, well maybe not more remarkable, but
also remarkable is the fact that we're
looking at resting metabolic rate. If
you have some background in metabolism,
you'll know what I'm talking about and
why these data are so remarkable. Your
total metabolism is made up of resting
metabolism, what we're going over, but
also physical activity and a slight
metabolic burden from eating, called the
thermic effect of food. It seems
reasonable that when you're wearing a
weighted vest, your physical activity
based metabolism might climb simply
because you're well, you're moving more
weight. Or one could argue that uh you
might move less because it's an added
energy cost. However, we're not talking
about that form of metabolism. We're
discussing resting metabolism. So, if
you're sitting calmly without moving
around, your body is consuming more
energy than normal, which is
fascinating. It's especially fascinating
because those who didn't wear the vest
experienced an over 200 calorie
reduction in resting metabolism. And one
could argue that maybe they lost muscle
mass, which is energetically expensive.
But muscle isn't that expensive. So it
seems highly unlikely this is explained
in the vesties by simply maintaining
muscle mass. I think something else may
be going on here possibly through that
gravitto mechanism that we discussed
earlier. Either way, uh these are
fascinating findings. So in total, this
pilot study indicates that weighted
vests do two things. One, they help us
maintain some weight and likely fat loss
over long stretches of time. Two, they
preserve our largest part of our
metabolism, resting metabolism. Would
love to see more data on this topic. But
what's this? More data right here along
with personal experiences and what to
watch out for. I'll catch you over
there. Bestie investy.